Guide to the Thomas W. Streeter Collection of Austin Family and Texas Revolution Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Thomas W. Streeter Collection of Austin Family and Texas Revolution Papers
1786-1942
1814-1858
WA MSS S-3000
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.63
(2 boxes)
Legal and financial documents, correspondence, and military records documenting the history of Texas and the Spanish Southwest. Included is manuscript material generated by the families of Moses and Stephen F. Austin during the settlement of Texas; military records pertaining to the Mier Expedition and the capture of San Antonio de Bexar during the Texas Revolution; and Thomas W. Streeter's research files on the history of Texas and the Spanish Southwest.
Streeter, Thomas W. (Thomas Winthrop), 1883-1965
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Austin Family Papers, 1786-1858. II. Texas Revolution Papers, 1836-1852. III. Thomas W. Streeter Research Files, 1942, undated.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Thomas W. Streeter
Thomas W. Streeter (1883–1965), businessman, collector, and bibliographer, was born in New Hampshire and received degrees from Dartmouth College (B.L., 1904) and Harvard Law School (LL.B., 1907). Streeter worked as a businessman, including in the oil industry. He retired in 1939 and devoted his time to collecting and bibliography for Americana and Texana.
Streeter compiled the five volume Bibliography of Texas 1795-1845, published in three parts. In 1957, he sold his collection of Texas imprints to Yale University.
Stephen F. Austin
Stephen F. Austin (1793–1836), founder of Anglo-American Texas, was born in Virginia to Moses Austin and Maria Brown Austin. Moses Austin moved his family from Virginia to Missouri in pursuit of opportunities managing lead mines. After this pursuit failed, Moses traveled to San Antonio in 1820, where he made a successful request for a land grant in Spanish Texas and the ability to bring 300 families to the region. Moses was aided in this endeavor by his association with the Baron de Bastrop, who encouraged the governor of Spanish Texas, Antonio Maria Martinez, to accept Austin's bid.
Moses Austin died of pneumonia shortly after his return to Missouri, and Stephen assumed responsibility for the settlement charge. Austin began bringing settlers to Texas in 1821, shortly after Mexico achieved independence from Spain. Austin managed immigration and established and maintained the land system from the colony's capital, San Felipe de Austin. He also had civil and military control over the colony until 1828, when the Constitution of Coahuila and Texas went into effect and facilitated integration of the colony into the larger Mexican government.
Upon Mexico's independence from Spain, the Mexican government began to have growing concerns about revolutionary activities in Texas. In 1831, Austin was arrested in Mexico City on allegations of attempting to incite insurrection; he was freed in July 1835 and returned to Texas. Later that year, the Texas Revolution began. Texas achieved independence in June 1836, and Austin was appointed the Republic's first Secretary of State. He died in office two months later, on December 27, 1836. His sister Emily Austin Perry's husband, James F. Perry, served as executor of his estate. After Austin's death and the independence of the Republic of Texas, border disputes with Mexico continued, such as in the Mier Expedition of 1842.
Scope and Contents
Manuscript legal and financial documents, correspondence, and military records documenting the history of Texas and the Spanish Southwest. Included is manuscript material generated by the families of Moses and Stephen F. Austin during the settlement of Texas, including an 1827 transcription of the will of Baron de Bastrop; military records pertaining to the Mier Expedition and the capture of San Antonio de Bexar during the Texas Revolution; and Thomas W. Streeter's research files on the history of Texas and the Spanish Southwest.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Thomas W. Streeter, 1962.
Land grants -- Texas; Real property -- Texas; Coahuila and Texas (Mexico) -- Colonization; Coahuila (Mexico: State); Mexico -- Foreign relations -- Texas; Texas -- Colonization; Texas -- Emigration and immigration; Texas -- Foreign relations -- Mexico; Texas -- History -- 1846-1950; Texas -- History -- Republic, 1836-1846; Texas -- History -- Revolution, 1835-1836; Texas -- History -- To 1846; Texas -- Politics and government; Land grants -- Texas -- 19th century; Legal documents -- Texas -- 19th century; Military records -- Mexico -- 19th century; Wills -- Texas -- 19th century; Conveyances -- Texas -- 19th century; Streeter, Thomas W. (Thomas Winthrop), 1883-1965; Austin, Moses, 1761-1821; Austin, Stephen F. (Stephen Fuller), 1793-1836; Bastrop, Felipe Enrique Neri, Baron de, 1759-1827
- Austin Family Papers, 1786-1858; Series I; 8
  Arrangement
  The order in which this previously uncataloged collection was arranged has been maintained.
  - Moses Austin and John Rice Jones papers concerning the dispute over the Mine à Breton, 1786-1797 (Box 1)
  - San Felipe de Austin and early Texas papers, 1814-1858; 3 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes a 1827 manuscript transcription of the will of Baron de Bastrop; land grants for territory in San Felipe de Austin, San Antonio de Bexar, and the Matagorda League; correspondence concerning land allocations; financial records concerning the Austin family's finances; a 1843 letter to Santa Anna concerning a plan to make peace with the Texans; and a 1831 manuscript petition from Hosea H. League and Seth Ingram to be released from the San Felipe de Austin jail.
  - Stephen F. Austin estate papers, 1837-1854; 4 (Box 1)
- Texas Revolution Papers, 1836-1852; Series II; 5
  - Mier expedition papers, 1842-1843; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Includes original manuscript documents, 20th century typed English translations, and photostats of unidentified related documents.
  - Capture of San Antonio de Bexar, 1836-1836 (Box 1)
    Manuscript inventory of soldiers defending San Antonio, 1836; manuscript description of the dead and wounded, 1836; manuscript document justifying the capture of San Antonio, 1836; and photostats and 20th century English translations of unidentified related documents.
  - Military records documenting the court martial of Brigadier Major General Gabriel R. Paul, 1852-1852 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript letter from the Convention of Massachusetts concerning the annexation of Texas, 1845-1845 (Box 1)
- Thomas W. Streeter Research Files, 1942; Series III; 3
  - Photostats and other copies of material related to the Spanish Southwest from the John Carter Brown Library, 1942, undated (Box 2)
  - Typed transcriptions and translations of unidentified material relating to the history of the Spanish Southwest, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)